Guide to the New York State National Guard, 9th Regiment Collection 1812-1961 MS 3085
New-York Historical Society
New York State National Guard, 9th Regiment collection
1812-1961
New-York Historical Society
New York (State). National Guard. Regiment, 9th
Veterans of the 9th Regiment Association
MS 3085
12.46 Linear feet in eleven boxes of various sizes, fourteen free standing volumes, and one oversized folder.
This collection contains materials relating to the New York State National Guard, 9th Regiment. This military unit saw active service during the Civil War, the Spanish-American War, World War I, and World War II. The unit was given many other formal designations over time, including the 83rd New York Volunteer Infantry Regiment during the Civil War, and the 244th Coastal Artillery. The contents of this collection were compiled over time by the Veterans of the Ninth Regiment and include Civil War company records, commissions and certificates, minute books of the Veterans Association, general and special orders, scrapbooks, photographs, photo albums, invitations, ephemera, newspaper clippings, programs, and correspondence.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Veterans of the Ninth Regiment, 1985-1986.
Arrangement
Arranged into six series:
Series I. Civil War Regimental Records (1860-1868, 1897)
Series II. Veteran Association Meeting Minutes (1869, 1871-1922)
Series III. Orders (1885-1941)
Series IV. Collected Documents (1814-1957)
Series V. Photograph Albums (1861-1945)
Series VI. Scrapbooks (1812-1950)
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials relating to the New York State National Guard, 9th Regiment. This military unit saw active service during the Civil War, the Spanish-American War, World War I, and World War II. While referred to as the 9th Regiment through the years, the unit was given many other formal designations over time, including the 83rd New York Volunteer Infantry Regiment (Civil War) and the 244th Coastal Artillery. The contents of this collection were compiled over time by the Veterans of the Ninth Regiment and include some Civil War company records, commissions and certificates, minute books of the veterans' and officers' associations, general and special orders, scrapbooks, photographs, photograph albums, invitations, newspaper clippings, programs, and correspondence.
Civil War era material includes several records from Companies A, C, I, and L including descriptive rolls, clothing reports, and morning reports; a petition from the regiment requesting release from service; a roll book for Company L said to have been taken from the corpse of a sergeant at Gettysburg; one edition of the regiment's camp newspaper; four albums of cartes-de-visite of officers and enlisted men who fought in the war; and other documents. Minute books for the Veterans Association span from 1871 to 1922, and there is a minute book for the Officers' Association of the 9th Coast Artillery Corps for 1917-1939. There is an extensive series of general and special orders from about 1890 to 1940 detailing daily activities, notifications for special events, enlistment information of certain men, and more.
Much of the collection pulls together a variety of collected documents, photographs and scrapbooks that collectively illustrate the history of the regiment from the early 1800s to the 1950s. Individual soldiers are represented with commissions, discharge papers, photographs, and other documents, especially for the 1870s and later. Colonel James Roosevelt Hitchcock (died 1878) features prominently in this regard. Several files include histories and historical notes about the regiment, helping to trace its lineage and actions into the mid-twentieth century. There is a rich set of ephemera, including programs and invitations, related to the social activities of the 9th Regiment and the Veterans Association. There are many photographs, both in the albums and standalone, of the regiment in training camps. The container list attempts to provide a more detailed view of the varied content in the collection
Biographical / Historical
The 9th Regiment was first formed on June 24, 1799 as the "6th Regiment of Infantry (N.Y.N.G.)." On March 27, 1805, the designation of the regiment was changed from the "6th Regiment of Infantry" to the "2nd Regiment of Artillery in New York City" and on June 13, 1812, the designation was changed once again to the "9th Regiment of Artillery." On December 13, 1813, the regiment was reduced to a battalion and on June 6, 1816, the battalion was reorganized as a regiment using the name "1st Battalion of the New York State Artillery."
The 9th Regiment participated (at intervals) in the War of 1812. It was in active service for roughly one year, in and about New York City, and was part of the U.S. Forces stationed at Sag Harbor in Long Island, N.Y., though the regiment did not participate in the conflict.
During the Mexican-American War, the 9th Regiment offered its services, however, the size of the unit was too small, not conforming to the U.S. military's size requirement.
On May 29, 1850, the unit became known as the "9th Regiment, New York State Militia" and due to the large percentage of Irish soldiers within the regiment, it was given the nickname, "the Irish Ninth."
Between 1861 and 1864, the 9th Regiment saw combat during the Civil War and fought under the name of the "83rd New York Volunteer Infantry Regiment." It was attached to the Army of the Potomac and participated in dozens of actions from 1861 to 1864 including the battles of Antietam, Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, Gettysburg, the Wilderness, Spotsylvania Court House, and Cold Harbor to name some of the more famous engagements.
During the Spanish-American War, the regiment served as the "9th New York Volunteer Infantry" and increased in size to a twelve company regiment. This larger company was later disbanded in December 1898.
On January 23, 1908, in accordance with military law, the 9th Regiment was converted to coast artillery, becoming part of the Coast Artillery Corps and New York's National Guard as the 9th Artillery District.
In addition to participating in military conflicts, during the nineteenth century, the 9th Regiment was called to service during the abolition riots of 1835, the great fire in New York City of 1845, the Orange riot of 1871 and the three railroad riots of 1877, 1892, and 1895 at Albany, Buffalo, and Brooklyn respectively.
On August 5, 1917, the unit was mustered into federal service and assigned to Coast Defenses of Sandy Hook, New Jersey. During its World War I service, the 9th Regiment was reorganized as the 9th Regiment, C.A.C., N.Y.G., and also given the designation of Coast Defense Command. The unit was demobilized in December 1918 at Fort Hancock, organized as a depot battalion and transferred to 8th Coast Artillery Corps.
On January 11, 1918, some companies within the 9th Regiment were reassigned to the 57th Artillery, Coast Artillery Corps and served in France. These troops later returned to the U.S. and were demobilized in February 1919.
In 1920, the regiment was reorganized and redesignated as the "9th Coast Defense Command, New York National Guard (N.Y.N.G.)". In 1924, they were once again renamed the "244th Artillery, Coast Artillery (Tractor Drawn) Regiment, Coast Artillery Corps." Regiments of this type were usually armed with 24 155 mm GPF guns on towed mounts.
Inducted once again into federal service on September 16, 1940, the unit was moved to Camp Pendleton in Virginia. The 9th participated in military maneuvers in North Carolina between September 29, 1941 and December 3, 1941.
On December 21, 1941 1st Battalion was transferred to Fort Macon, North Carolina, where they established the Temporary Harbor Defenses of Beaufort, NC. From July 1942 until September 1942, reinforced by the 2nd Battalion, 54th Coast Artillery (Colored), the 9th served at Fort Macon until they were relieved by 3rd Battalion, 2nd Coast Artillery. 1st Battalion was then moved via the New York Port of Embarkation to the United Kingdom. Once they arrived in Honiton, England, the 1st Battalion was reorganized and redesignated as the 633rd AAA Auto-Weapons Battalion. This unit landed in France on June 16, 1944 and served in the European theater until returned to New York and inactivated October 6, 1945.
On December 24, 1941 2nd Battalion moved to Fort Lewis, Washington, where they were set to be deployed to Alaska. The 2nd Battalion was inactivated in Alaska on June 5, 1944 and redesignated the "289th Coast Artillery Battalion" (155 mm gun). They were then moved to Camp Joseph T. Robinson in Arkansas. Once in Arkansas, on August 17, 1944, 2nd Battalion was redesignated as the "782nd Field Artillery Battalion" (8-inch howitzer). This unit was further redesignated as the "782nd Chemical Mortar Battalion" on July 5, 1945 at Camp Bowie in Texas. They were later inactivated on September 8, 1945.
3rd Battalion departed Camp Pendleton on January 17, 1942 and deployed to New Caledonia in the South Pacific. On January 20, 1943, the 3rd Battalion was redesignated as the "259th Coast Artillery Battalion" (155 mm gun). This unit deployed to Guadalcanal, Fiji, New Guinea, and the Philippines. They were later deactivated on August 20, 1945 in the Philippines.
It should also be noted that between 1859 to 1969, the 9th Regiment's armory was located at 125 West 14th Street in Manhattan. The armory was later destroyed in the 1970s.
[The information for this note was derived from Wikipedia, the New York State Military Museum and Veterans Research Center, as well as the collection itself (Box 5/Folder 14, and others).]
Camp Pendleton (Va.); Fishers Island (N.Y.); Fort Ontario (N.Y.); New York (State) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Peekskill (N.Y.); Sandy Hook (N.J.); Certificates.; Clippings (information artifacts); Letters (correspondence); Military records.; Minute books.; Muster rolls.; Orders (military records).; Photograph albums.; Printed ephemera.; Scrapbooks.; Artillery, Coast; Military camps -- New York (State); Spanish-American War, 1898; Veterans -- New York (State); World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.; New York (State). National Guard. 244th Coast Artillery; United States. Army. Engineer Combat Battalion, 633rd; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 83rd (1861-1864); Hitchcock, James Roosevelt, -1878
- Series I: Civil War Regimental Records, 1860-1868, 1897; .58 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series relates to the 9th Regiment's service in the Civil War, when it was designated the 83rd Regiment of New York State Volunteers. The series contains a small number of company records, specifically for Companies A, C, I, and L. Record books represented in the series are descriptive, clothing, roll, morning reports, and regimental orders. Morning reports provide the best insight into the activities of the companies as they include brief descriptions of every day's events. (This series centers on records that were created in the field using the official report forms made available to the regiments. See also Series IV, V, and VI for additional documents and photographs that relate to the Civil War era.)
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged mainly by company.
  - Company A Clothing Book, 1861-1864 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 1)
    Entries listing the company's soldier name, place of enlistment, date of entry, list of clothes issued, and monetary values of said items. Over 100 pages of entries. Records of items (including ordnance) received from the quartermaster can be found after many blank pages at the back of the volume.
  - Company A Morning Reports, 1864 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 2)
    Contains "Remarks for the Month" and a log recording attendance of soldiers in regiment, as well as any additions/losses to regiment.
  - Company C Morning Reports, 1861-1864 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 3)
  - Company I Descriptive Book, 1864-1868, 1897 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 4)
    Book lists names of officers, non-commissioned officers, deaths, deserters, and summary of what happened to each soldier. An 1897 introductory note to the volume provides context, indicating that it was started in April 1864 and updated with information over time as it became available to the recordkeeper.
  - Company I Morning Reports, 1863-1864 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 5)
  - Company L Clothing Book, 1861-1864 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 6)
    Contains soldier names, regiment, place of enlistment, date of entry, list of clothes issued, and monetary values of said items.
  - Company L Descriptive Book, 1861-1864 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 7)
    Book lists names of officers, non-commissioned officers, deaths, deserters, and summary of what happened to each soldier.
  - Company L Morning Reports, 1861-1864 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 8)
  - Regimental Order Book, 1863-1864 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 9)
    Transcriptions of special orders 1 through 32 and two letters.
- Series II: Veterans Association Meeting Minutes, 1869, 1871-1922; .75 Linear feet
  This series contains minute books of the Veterans of the Ninth Regiment N.G.S.N.Y. (1871-1922) and the Board of Trustees for the Association (1900-1918). For the most part, the contents discuss veteran related affairs, including arrangements for banquets, commemmorations, and other events, as well as various financial and administrative matters.
  This series is organized in chronological order. One volume of Board of Trustees minutes that overlaps in time with the Association minutes is at the end.
  - Minutes. Veterans of the Ninth Regiment, N.G.S.N.Y., 1869, 1871-1885 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 30)
    A circular of 1869 in the volume, and the subject matter of the earliest entries in the volume (1871) suggest that these were the first, or earliest documented, meetings of the Veterans Association.
  - Minutes. Veterans of the Ninth Regiment, N.G.S.N.Y., 1885 September-1892 September (Offsite-box 13, Volume 10)
  - Minutes. Veterans of the Ninth Regiment, N.G.S.N.Y., 1892 October-1899 December (Offsite-box 13, Volume 11)
  - Minutes. Veterans of the Ninth Regiment, N.G.S.N.Y., 1900 January-1912 February (Offsite-box 13, Volume 12)
  - Minutes. Veterans of the Ninth Regiment, N.G.S.N.Y., 1912 March-1922 December (Offsite-box 13, Volume 13)
  - Minutes. Board of Trustees of the Veterans of the Ninth Regiment, N.G.S.N.Y. -- N.Y.S.M. -- 83rd Vols., 1900-1918 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 31)
    At back of volume is a mimeographed copy of the constitution of the Veterans Association of the Ninth Regiment, as amended November 11, 1916.
- Series III: Orders, 1885-1941; 3.25 Linear feet
  This series consists of general and special orders sent to the regiment from various levels of command. Orders include daily activities, notifications for special events, enlistment of men, and more.
  The series is arranged by type of order (general, special) and issuing agency. The order is generally chronological within each group. Within each year the documents are in reverse chronological order, as they were originally when bound. One set of orders from 1898 is in a freestanding volume.
  - General Orders. Regimental Headquarters (6 Folders), 1885-1940 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8-13)
    There is one 1885 order and one 1888 order from headquarters of the 9th Regiment. From September 1988 and later, the orders are from the regimental headquarters of the various designations given the 9th Regiment over time: 9th Regiment, First Brigade (September 1888 through 1907), 9th Coast Artillery District (1908-February 1911), 9th Artillery District (March 1911-August 1914), 9th Coast Defense Command (September 1914-1923), and 244th Coast Artillery (1924-1940).
  - General Orders. Regimental Headquarters (1 volume), 1901 January-1915 December (Offsite-box 13, Volume 14)
    This is a bound set of general orders that partially overlaps the date range of the above orders, though a comparison was not made to determine whether the content is completely redundant for that period. These bound orders appear to be signed as official, while that is not necessarily so for the same orders in the above folders.
  - Orders. Headquarters, Ninth Regiment, 1898 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    Handwritten orders on letterhead of the 9th Regiment HQ, with most orders relating to the state camp of instruction, Camp Townsend, near Peekskill, NY.
  - Special Orders. Regimental Headquarters (12 of 16 folders), 1917-1933 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-12)
    Orders from the 9th Coast Artillery Corps until mid 1919, then 9th Coast Defense Command until early 1924, then 244th Artillery to the end in 1940.
  - Special Orders. Regimental Headquarters (4 of 16 folders), 1934-1940 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Special Orders. Adjutant General's Office (4 Folders), 1916-1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11-14)
  - Special Orders. Commanding General National Guard (3 Folders), 1920-1940 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5-7)
    Generally on letterhead of the New York National Guard.
- Series IV: Collected Documents, 1814-1961; 2.79 Linear feet
  The "Collected Documents" series contains various documents collected and compiled by the Veterans of the Ninth Regiment. Items include: correspondence, newspaper articles, photographs, certificates, official military paperwork, enlistment paperwork, discharge paperwork, orders, newspaper clippings, sheet music, invitations, programs, ephemera, muster rolls, booklets, and more. A large portion of this series focuses upon the military service of individual soldiers. There are also typed histories of the regiment relating to specific time periods as well as folders relating to specific military conflicts.
  This series is, for the most part, arranged by topic and advances in rough chronological order. This chronology is based on the history of the regiment that extends from the late 1700s to the 1950s. The date ranges shown in the container list reflect the actual date of the documents.
  With minor exception, the content of each subject folder remains as found by the processing archivist in 2019, which was likely the content as originally donated to N-YHS by the Veterans Association. The sequence of the folders was refined in 2019, but generally follows that, retains the order of material as found by the processing archivist in 2019.
  - Record of Colonel Jacob Morton (commissioned 1799-1805), 1908-1910 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Papers relating to the identity and war service of Morton, with transcriptions of 1808-1810 documents. The original documents in the folder are correspondence from 1908-1909; here Morton's family was conducting a genealogy project seeking to learn more about his role during the Revolutionary War. Folder also contains a portrait of Governor John Jay; he formed the Ninth Regiment on June 24, 1799 (undated portrait).
  - Record of Colonel Lebbeus Loomis (commissioned 1807-1811), 1901, 1907-1919 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    Documents relating to the history of Loomis's service with the 9th Regiment during the Revolutionary War, as well as genealogy requests. Includes a copy of "An Index to Taintor's Colchester (Conn.) Records" (1901).
  - Major John J. Earle, 1814-1824, 1907 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    Papers relating to Major John J. Earle. Documents include: letter from Earle's daughter asking for information about her father's military service, as well as several original promotion certificates.
  - Presentation of Sword to Lafayette by 9th Regiment (1824), 1895 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
    Papers relating to the history of Lafayette and his sword, as well as regimental orders regarding the presentation of this sword to Lafayette. Typescript of related 1824 regimental order.
  - Colonel Samuel J. Hunt (commissioned 1826-1834), 1827, 1891, 1950 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    Folder contains a photograph (cabinet card) of Hunt in 1891 and a circular of a Regimental Order concerning former Captain Samuel W. Seely's response to charges brought against him by Colonel Hunt (1827), with 1950 letter from Mills Miller transmitting the circular.
  - Warrant of Robert P. Getty as 1st Sergeant, 9th Regiment, 1835 June (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
  - Colonels of the 9th Regiment (1829-1900), circa 1870s?-1900 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
    Folder includes portraits (photographs and printed engravings) of: Col. James Lefferts (service 1829-1834, photo undated), Col. Henry Utterberg Slipper (service 1834-1867, photo undated), Col. Jasper Langdon Curtis (service 1843-1846, photo undated), Col. Ebenezer Jesup Jr. (service 1846-1848, undated photo of a drawing), Col. Benjamin Clinton Ferris (service 1848-1855, undated photo of a drawing), Col. Charles R. Braine (service 1859-1874, photo 1874(?) and engraving), Col. S. Oscar Ryder (service 1879-1882, undated engraving), Col. William Seward Jr. (service 1882-1898, undated engraving), Col. Goodman Jasper Greene (photo 1898), and Col. William F. Morris (photo 1900).
  - Reception of Major General Winfield Scott, 1849 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
    Folder holds one booklet. Full title: "Report of the Joint Special Committee of the Common Council appointed for the purpose of making suitable arrangements for the reception of Major General Scott on his return from Mexico, and to tender to him the hospitalities of the city." Document No. 62 of the Board of Aldermen. May 15, 1948.
  - The 9th Regiment as an Irish Regiment (1850s), 1917, 1950s? (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
    Folder contains two documents with notes on the Irish presence in the regiment's history, and a photocopy of an 1854 circular from Lt. Colonel Sweeny and Major Shea to the rank and file of the regiment concerning their resignations.
  - New York City Guard (Folder 1 of 2), circa 1840-1850 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
    Folder contains the "City Guard Quick Step" sheet music. See second folder for oversized content.
  - New York City Guard (Folder 2 of 2), Oversize, 1858 (Folder OS-Medium)
    Printed muster roll of Company G (with 1943 transmittal letter)
  - Appointment Certificates, 1855-1866 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
    This folder contains a Private's certificate of membership for Lui Froideraux (1855) and for Alexander Barbey (1866), and an appointment as Right General Guide for Edward B. Welles (1859)
  - Civil War (3 folders), 1861-1864, 1902-1913 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12a-c)
    Folder 12a includes a return of officers and enlisted men absent from Company F (1863); a testimonial to Captain J.B.C. Murray (1862); 3 letters ((1861-63); a pass to travel from Norfolk to Bermuda Hundred, VA. (1864); by-laws of the "Night Owls," formed by Company C at Fort Smith, MD (1861); the August 7, 1862 edition of "The New York Ninth" newspaper issued at Warrenton, VA; "The Soldier's Hymn Book," published by the New-York Young Men's Christian Association; and a roll book for Company L, taken from the body of Sgt. Curry at Gettysburg. Folder 12b includes photographs of Col. Michael Van Beuren (service 1840-1861), Col. John Hendrickson (service 1863) and 2nd Lt. Charles Barker (killed at Spotsylvania, 1864); and engravings of Col. John W. Stiles (1861-1863), Col. And B'V'T' Brig-Gen John Hendrickson (1863), Col. Joseph A. Moesch (1863-1864), and Col. and B'V'T' Brig-Gen John H. Wilcox (1864-1869). There are also two photographs of the regiment's tattered battle flags. Folder 12c includes clippings and post-war notes; notable is a 1902 address by Col. William Heermance to the 9th Regiment Veterans titled "The Cavalry at Gettysburg."
  - Petition from the 9th Regiment (83rd Regiment N.Y. Volunteers) (1 of 2), 1863 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)